Guide to the John Lowenthal Papers TAM.190
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
John Lowenthal Papers
1934-2004
TAM.190
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
32.5 linear feet in 34 records cartons and 4 oversize folders.
John Lowenthal (1925-2003) was an attorney and filmmaker. While in law school Lowenthal had a brief stint as a volunteer assistant to the defense during Alger Hiss's two perjury trials in 1949 and 1950. In the 1970s, after the release of suppressed FBI documents about the case, Lowenthal, by then a Rutgers University law professor, published an analysis of what this new evidence revealed. Several years later, Lowenthal took a leave from Rutgers to make "The Trials of Alger Hiss," a feature-length documentary film about the case. The John Lowenthal Papers consists primarily of materials gathered for Lowenthal's film, "The Trials of Alger Hiss" (Los Angeles, California: Direct Cinema, Ltd., 1981). The collection includes research files and transcripts of the interviews conducted for the film, correspondence, court records, and rough drafts and typescripts of articles and commentary written by Lowenthal. NOTE: Series I, Alger Hiss Research Files, has been microfilmed (R-7771C) NOTE: This collection is located offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Lowenthal, John
Provenance
The John Lowenthal Papers were donated to the Tamiment Library by John Lowenthal in 2003.
Other Finding Aids note
The microfilmed portion of this collection (Series I, Boxes 1-5) and the microfilmed portions of several other collections related to Alger Hiss at this repository form the microfilm edition of the Papers of Alger Hiss (comprised of Film R-7771B, R-7771C, R-7771D, and R-7771E). A published guide to the Papers of Alger Hiss microfilm edition is available at this repository (call number REF E743.5.H55 P38 2006).
Microfilm
Series I, Boxes 1-5 of the collection are available on microfilm (Film R-7771C) for use in this repository only. Researchers must use microfilm for this portion of the collection.
Access Restrictions
NOTE: This collection is located offsite and advance notice is required for use. Researchers must use microfilm for Series I, Boxes 1-5 (Film R-7771C). There is a published guide for the microfilmed portion of the collection (call number REF E743.5.H55 P38 2006). The guide also details portions of other collections related to Alger Hiss at this repository which have been microfilmed.
Historical/Biographical Note
John Lowenthal (1925-2003) was an attorney and filmmaker. He was born in Manhattan on May 14, 1925. He served in the Navy and attended Columbia College and Columbia University School of Law (class of 1950). While in law school, Lowenthal spent some time as a volunteer assistant to the defense during Alger Hiss's two perjury trials in 1949 and 1950.
In the 1970s, after the release of suppressed FBI documents about the case, Lowenthal, by then a Rutgers University law professor, published an analysis of what this new evidence revealed. Several years later, Lowenthal took a leave from Rutgers to make "The Trials of Alger Hiss," a feature-length documentary film about the case, released in 1980. Lowenthal worked closely with Hiss on the film, which used a series of new interviews and presented evidence that had been withheld from the jury that found Hiss guilty of perjury.
With the collapse of the Soviet Union, Lowenthal, on Hiss's behalf, asked Russian General Dimitry Antonovich Volkogonov, a biographer of Stalin and at the time military advisor to President Boris Yeltsin, to search Soviet files for any evidence that Alger Hiss had been either a Communist or a spy. In the mid-1990s, Lowenthal was one of the first legal scholars to challenge the assertion that the National Security Agency's then just-released "Venona" cables -- coded wartime messages sent home from the United States by Soviet operatives and then intercepted and decrypted -- supported the allegation that Hiss had been engaged in espionage on behalf of the Soviet Union. In 2003, Lowenthal successfully defended a Hiss-related libel action brought against him in London by Alexander Vassiliev, a former KGB agent and co-author (with Allen Weinstein) of The Haunted Wood, a study of Soviet espionage in the U.S. Vassiliev sued Frank Cass and Company, publishers of Lowenthal's article, "Venona and Alger Hiss" in the journal Intelligence and National Security. The libel action asserted that Lowenthal, in his article, had called Vassiliev an "unreliable author whose identification of persons who worked for the KGB is in part wrong, in part based on out-of-context information, and in part mere guesswork." On June 13, 2003, the jury threw out the case.
In the years after the release of his film, Lowenthal taught at the New School for Social Research and at the CUNY Law School at Queens College. He was also a classical cellist who performed widely. John Lowenthal died of cancer in London, where he had made his home for some years, on September 9, 2003.
Scope and Content Note
Series I. Alger Hiss Research Files, 1934-2004. This series consists primarily of materials gathered for Lowenthal's film, "The Trials of Alger Hiss" (Los Angeles, California: Direct Cinema, Ltd.). The series includes transcripts of the interviews conducted for the film with Alger Hiss, Donald Hiss and his wife, Mike, Pat and Raymond Catlett, Ramos Feehan, Gussie Feinstein, Vincent Shaw, Margaret Halsey, Harold Rosenwald, Edward Murtagh, Malcolm Cowley, Isaac Don Levine, Nathan Witt, Ralph de Toledano, Robert Stripling, Sam Krieger, Harold Shapero, Ordman Clubb, John Francis Cronin, and David Zalodowski, among others, and a campaign speech on the Hiss Case by President Richard Nixon. The series also includes correspondence between Lowenthal and the Hiss family -- Alger, Anna, Donald, Isabel, Priscilla, and Tony - as well as Alger Hiss biographical information, interviews, notices of lectures and seminars, a typescript on the New Deal, letters of support and materials relating to Hiss's reinstatement to the Massachusetts State Bar. Materials directly pertaining to the Hiss Case include the Baltimore Exhibits and evaluation by Edward H. Fearon, FBI interviews, government exhibits, trial notes and samples from five Woodstock typewriters, and three original letters from Whittaker Chambers to Mark Van Doren. Materials pertaining to Russian Archives, Soviet Intelligence and the Venona Documents include files on Georgi Abratov, Boris Bykov, Alexander Vassiliev, Vitali Pavlov and Dmitri Volkogonov. NOTE: Series I. Alger Hiss Research Files, 1934-2004 was microfilmed as part of the collection, "Alger Hiss Papers at the Tamiment Library," (Thomson Gale Publishers); microfilm call number R-7771.
Series II. Subject Files, 1942-2004. This series (not microfilmed) consists primarily of research and background materials gathered during the making of the film, "The Trials of Alger Hiss." Included are copies of court records from the first Hiss trial and legal files concerning Hiss's appeal. The series also includes correspondence between John Lowenthal and Bruce Craig, Agnese Nelms Haury, Victor Navasky, and others; comments and criticism regarding Lowenthal's writings; materials documenting discussions with potential funding sources and distributors of the film; reviews of the film and publicity material. Other files in this series include include John's father Max Lowenthal's Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) file, a typescript of William A. Reuben's unpublished study of the Hiss Case; and Hugh Whitemore's typescripts for various television productions on Whittaker Chambers and Hiss. Materials pertaining to Soviet/Russian archives, Soviet Intelligence and the Venona Documents include files on Boris Bykov and Alexander Vassiliev.
Series III. Addendum, 1949-1993. This small series (.25 linear ft.) contains correspondence of John Lowenthal, including letters to his family from a trip to Paris in the summer of 1949, as well as correspondence relating to Alger Hiss. There also a file on the Agnese Helms Naury trust, several letters by Anne Lowenthal, an article on Whittaker Chambers' employment by, and dismissal from, the New York Public Library, a brochure for the film, The Trials of Alger Hiss, and a 1992 newspaper clipping, "Vindication for Alger Hiss."
NOTE: Researchers must use microfilm for series I. Alger Hiss Research Files, 1934-2003; microfilm call number R-7771C.
Arrangement
Folders arranged alphabetically by topic in series I and II.
The files are grouped into three series:
I, Alger Hiss Research Files, 1934-2004
II, Subject Files, 1942-2004
III, Addendum
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Related materials providing biographical information on Alger Hiss and information on the Hiss case can be found in the following collections in this repository (researchers must use microfilm where indicated):
Agnese Nelms Haury Papers, TAM 163 (Series 1, Boxes 1 and 2 on microfilm, Film R-7771D)
Alger Hiss Family Papers, TAM 314 (on microfilm, Film R-7771B: Series 1, Boxes 1-3; Series 2, Boxes 4-5; and Series 3, Box 6)
William A. Reuben Papers, TAM 289 (Series 1, Box 1 on microfilm, Film R-7771E)
A published guide to the microfilmed portions of these collections is available at this repository (call number REF E743.5.H55 P38 2006).
The Alger Hiss Defense Collection housed at the Harvard Law School Library, Harvard University consists of 115 boxes of materials amassed by Hiss's lawyers and additional materials related to Hiss's defense donated by Hiss researchers and supporters. The first three series of the Alger Hiss Defense Collection (Hiss Defense Files Series I, Hiss Defense Files Series II, and Hiss-Chambers Subject Files) are available at this repository on microfilm (Film R-7771A) and have an associated published guide (call number REF E743.5.H55 P37 2006). Materials excluded from the microfilm are available to researchers who use the collection on site at the Harvard Law School Library at Harvard University.
Chambers, Whittaker; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Craig, R. Bruce.; Hiss, Alger; Hiss, Alger -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Hiss, Priscilla Fansler; Hiss, Tony.; Lockwood, Agnese Nelms; Lowenthal, Anne.; Lowenthal, David.; Lowenthal, John; Lowenthal, Max.; Nation Institute (U.S.).; Navasky, Victor S.; Rabinowitz, Victor.; Reuben, William A.; Smith, John Chabot.; United Nations.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities.; Volkogonov, Dmitri Antonovich.; Weinstein, Allen; Articles.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Espionage, Soviet |z United States.; Personal papers.; Research (document genres).; Trials (Perjury) |z United States.
- Series I: Alger Hiss Research Files, 1934-2003
  Access Restrictions
  Patrons must use microfilm: microfilm call number R-7771
  - Agricultural Adjustment Administration: "Purge", 1935, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alger Hiss Soviet Archives Project, undated, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Civil Liberties Union: Re: Hiss Case, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anderson, Neil, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arbatov, Georgi: Institute for the United States and Canada, Director, Oct 13, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beer, Richards and Haller: Re: Typewriter, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Billington, James: Librarian of Congress, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bird, Kai: Re: Dmitri Volkogonov, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Borovik, Artyom: Re: Volkogonov and Obituaries, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brooks, Winfield: Re: "How the FBI Trapped Hiss" (American Weekly), 1950, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Burton, Margaret: Correspondence, Feb 28, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Buttenweiser, Helen, 1966, 1970, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chabot Smith, John, 1974-1975, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chambers, Whittaker: Clippings, 1948-1981, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chambers, Whittaker: Correspondence (see also Van Doren, Mark), May 25, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chambers, Whittaker: HUAC, Dec 6, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chambers, Whittaker: Medal of Freedom, 1984, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chambers, Whittaker: Memorandum of Conversation, Mar 20, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chambers, Whittaker: Pseudonyms, Oct 11, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1957, 1962-2000 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Re: In The Court of Public Opinion, Feb 1957 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Re: "Ales"/Venona, undated, 1996, 1999-2003 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cowley, Malcolm, 1948, 1977, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Craig, Bruce: Interview with Edward R. Pierce Re: Espionage, Feb 28, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Craig, Bruce: Re: HUAC/Grand Jury Testimony, 1998-2002 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Craig, Bruce: Trip Report, Edward R. Stettinius Papers, University of Virginia, Feb 23, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cronin, John: Interview, Jul 16, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dollard, Charles: President, Carnegie Corporation, Jan 21, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Duggan, Lawrence: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dupont Company: Interview with Officials, Apr 7, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Duvall, Frank: U.S. State Department, undated, 1948-1949, 1953-1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Eastman Kodak Company: Interviews with Officials, Jan 26, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Eddy, George, 1949-1950, 1962, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Feehan, Ramos: Re: Typewriter, 1948-1949, 1976-1977, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Feehan, Raymond, undated, 1948, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Field, Noel, 1993-1994, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA): Correspondence, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - FOIA: Documents, 1943, 1978, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Garlin, Sender, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Gorelov, Oleg, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Grimsted, Patricia Kennedy: Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Gwynn, Beatrice V.: "Clearing Alger Hiss," Typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gwynn, Beatrice V.: Correspondence, 1969-1972, 1976, 1993-2002 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Halsey, Margaret, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Haury, Agnese: Correspondence, 1996, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Haury, Agnese: Re: National Security Archive, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Heller, Howard: Re: Whittaker Chambers, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Herbst, Josephine, Dec 30, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hiss, Alger and "Ales" (Primakov et al.), 1996-2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hiss, Alger: Biographical Information, undated, 1934, 1948-1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Hiss, Alger: Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hiss, Alger: Correspondence, 1934, 1942, 1945-1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hiss, Alger: Correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hiss, Alger: Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Hiss, Alger: Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hiss, Alger: Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hiss, Alger: Correspondence, 1976-1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hiss, Alger: Correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Hiss, Alger: Correspondence, 1985-1988, 1990-1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Hiss, Alger: Correspondence, To Leo Pasvolsky (from the Edward R. Stettinius Jr. Papers, University of Virginia), Feb 14, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Hiss, Alger: Interview with Herbert Abrams, re: Yalta Conference, Apr 6, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Hiss, Alger: Interview, BBC, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Hiss, Alger: Interview with Richard Popkin, Transcript and Typescript, undated, 1964, 1966-1974 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Hiss, Alger: Interviews, Radio, Rutgers University, Television (US), 1962-1963, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Hiss, Alger: Lectures/Seminars, undated, 1967, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Hiss, Alger: Letters of Support, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hiss, Alger: Litigation Citations and Opinions, 1972, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Hiss, Alger: Pardon, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Hiss, Alger: Policy Review, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Hiss, Alger: Political Cartoons, re: Hiss, undated, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Hiss, Alger: Poster, "McCarthy and the Press," Presentation at the University of Pittsburgh, Oct 8, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Hiss, Alger: Re: Recollections of a Life, undated, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Hiss, Alger: Reinstatement to Massachusetts Bar, 1974-1975, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hiss, Alger: "The New Deal," Typescript., May 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hiss, Alger and William Reuben v. U.S. Department of Justice et al, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hiss, Alger: Re: Allen Weinstein, 1970, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hiss, Alger: Writings, 1973-1974, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hiss, Anna, undated, 1968, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hiss Case: Baltimore Documents Typed on Woodstock 230099, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Hiss Case: Cross, Claude, 1971-1972, 1975, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hiss Case: Donegan and Whearty, Dec 6, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hiss Case: Fearon, Edwin H., Document Comparison Charts, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Hiss Case: Fearon, Edwin H., Handwritten Baltimore Documents, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Hiss Case: Hiss Jury Project, "Approaching the Hiss Jurors", undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Hiss Case: Hiss Reply Brief, Feb 3, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Hiss Case: Horsky, Charles, undated, 1948, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hiss Case: Levi, Edward H., undated, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 14a)
  - Hiss Case: Norman, Daniel P., Photographs Annexed to Affidavit in re: U.S. v. Hiss No. c-128-402, Mar 7, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hiss Case: "Prosecutor Committed Grave Misconduct in Substantial Prejudice of Appellant's Rights", undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Hiss Case: "Pumpkin Papers", undated, 1949, 1974-1999 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Hiss Case: "Summary of the Position of Prosecutor T. F. Murphy and Mr. Ramos Feehan before the Opening of the Second Trial of Mr. Hiss", Oct 1949 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Hiss Case: Supplemental Affidavits in re: U.S. v. Alger Hiss, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Hiss Case: Surveillance of Defense, 19505, 1972, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Hiss Case: Trial Notes, undated, 1949-1950, 1977-1999 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hiss Case: Woodstock Typewriter, undated, 1963, 1969-1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Hiss Case: Woodstock Typewriter, 1949, 1957, 1962-1998 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Hiss Case: Woodstock Typewriter, Forgeries, undated, 1963-1964, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Hiss Case: Woodstock Typewriter, N230099, Samples, May 1970, Jan 1977 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Hiss Case: Woodstock Typewriter, N256978, Samples, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Hiss Case: Woodstock Typewriter, N319727, Samples, Apr 21, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Hiss Case: Woodstock Typewriter, N399212, Samples, Apr 21, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Hiss Case: Woodstock Typewriter, 8J163066, Samples, Mar 20, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Hiss Case: Woodstock Typewriter, Russell Bradford, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Hiss Case: Re: Yalta Conference, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Hiss, Donald, undated, 1948-1949, 1977-2002 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Hiss, Isabel Johnson, 1975, 2000, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Hiss, Priscilla Fansler, 1937, 1959, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Hiss, Tony: "Ales" Controversy, 1999-2003 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Hiss, Tony: Correspondence, 1973, 1976-1977, 1993-2003 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Hiss, Tony: Re: Typewriter, 1993, 1996-1997, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - HUAC: Report of Proceedings, Aug 5, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Hyde, Montgomery: Re: Typewriter, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Irons, Peter: Re: Horace Schmahl, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Jones, Cynthia Arden: FBI Interview, Jan 4, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Jones, Stephen: Re: Woodstock Typewriter, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Kalugin, Oleg: Interview, Jan 19, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Klehr, Harvey, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Kobaladze, Yuri: Foreign Intelligence Service of the Russian Federation, re: Hiss, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Koenigsberg, Samuel M.: Correspondence, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Kornberg, Harvey: "Bykov, Chambers, and Hiss: New Revelations About an Odd Relationship," Typescript, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lee, Eleanore: "The Elizabeth Bentley Matter," Typescript, 1983, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Levedev, I.: Re: Hiss, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Levin, Judith: Correspondence, May 16, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lindley, Agnese (Haury) (Mrs. Manice Lockwood III): Correspondence, 1976-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Lockwood, Manice, III: Re: Horace Schmahl, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Massing, Hede, 1948, 1950, 1981-2002 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Massing, Paul, 1945, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - McCarthy, Elizabeth: Re: Woodstock Typewriter, undated, 1941-1944, 1950-1970 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Meade, Bessie: (Reports on, by E.G.H.), 1966, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Murtagh, Arthur L: Re: Hiss, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - National Committee against Repressive Legislation: Tribute to Alger Hiss (Note: R-7771C/20 Begins Here), Jun 1984 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Nation Institute: Alger Hiss Research and Publication Project, 1998-2001 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Nation Institute: Alger Hiss Soviet Archives Project, undated, 1992-1993, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - National Emergency Civil Liberties Foundation (NECLF), 1975, 1978, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - NECLF: Hiss Defense Fund, undated, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Naumov, O: Re: Hiss, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Navasky, Victor, 1996, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Nikolaevich, Nikolai: Re: Hiss, Oct 1992, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Nixon, Richard: Speeches, re: Hiss, 1952, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Packer, Herbert: Re: Woodstock Typewriter, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Pavlov, Vitaliy, undated, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Penn, Arthur: Re: Sudoplatov/"Pumpkin Papers", 1994 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Piel, Eleanor Jackson: Correspondence, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Pikhovia, Rudolf Germanovich: Re: Hiss, undated, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Pilpel, Harriet: Correspondence, May 14, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Pressman, Lee: Re: Hiss, 1949, 1969, 1977-1994 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Rabinowitz, Victor: Re: Hiss, undated, 1983, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Raushenbush, Stephen: Correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Reuben, William A.: Hiss-Reuben FOIA Suit, 1974-1975, 1980, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Reuben, William A.: Re: Allen Weinstein, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Rosen, William, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Ruben, Albert: Correspondence, Sep 25, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Russian/Soviet Archives: Re: Hiss, undated, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Salant, Stephen: Re: FBI's Counter Intelligence Programs, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Salant, Stephen: Re: "Pumpkin Papers", undated, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Sayre, Francis B.: Correspondence, Jan 15, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Schroeter, Leonard: Correspondence, Apr 11, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Shattuck, John H.: American Civil Liberties Union, Nov 21, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Shepherd, Peter: Correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Solow, Robert: Re: FBI Interview, Jan 28, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Sproul, Kathleen: Correspondence, Apr 29, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Stevenson, Matthew: Re: "Ales", undated, 1987, 1995-2002 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Stossel, Frederic: Correspondence, May 2, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Tanenhaus, Sam, 1989-1993, 1998-2001 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Thron, C. Davis: Correspondence, 1974, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Toledano, Ralph de, 1950, 1957, 1977-1990 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Trials of Alger Hiss: Interviews, Alger Hiss (pp.1-70) (Note: R-7771C/21 Begins Here), Nov 9, 1976, Mar 7, 1978-Mar 8, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Trials of Alger Hiss: Interviews, Alger Hiss (pp.71-169), Nov 10, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Trials of Alger Hiss: Interviews, Alger Hiss (pp.170-252), Jan 22, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 56)